Now that we have a text editor to work with,
we're ready to dive into coding our HTML. Let's get started.
In our text editor, we're going to first set a few settings here
down in the bottom right corner.
I'm going to indent using spaces,
and I'm also going to set the tab with, or space with now,
to just 2 spaces.
This is just my own personal preference,
and you can actually go ahead and set these to whatever you want.
Now, in our text editor, we're going to create a file and save it as index.html.
In Sublime Text 2, you can create a new file by simply opening Sublime Text.
We're going to go ahead and on our Mac hit command S to save.
And we'll call this &quot;index.html&quot; and click save.
The reason we called the &quot;index&quot; is because most webservers
will look for this file name and serve it as the first page that a visitor sees.
This is often referred to as the homepage of your site.
We call it index, because it's usually an index or a listing of all the other things on the site.
The HTML extension is also important,
because when we open this file in a web browser,
the web browser will know to render the HTML and apply special formatting
rather than simply display the text as we see it in our editor.
Let's go ahead and switch over to our web browser,
which in this case is Google Chrome.
We'll go ahead and open up our index.html file.
I'm going to open our finder window here,
and I'll simply drag this onto Google Chrome to go ahead and open it.
Now, at this point we should just be seeing a blank webpage,
but pretty soon that'll change.
Now, in addition to our index.html file,
we're also starting off with a folder of images that Allison has put together for us.
Here we have a couple of icons, a few pictures of cupcakes,
our &quot;Smells like Bakin'&quot; logo, some more pictures of cupcakes,
a Twitter icon, and another image of cupcakes.
We'll be using all of these to create our &quot;Smells like Bakin'&quot; webpage.
Let's start coding.
We'll switch over to Sublime Text, and first, we're going to start our webpage with a doc type.
We're going to open our angle bracket, type an exclamation point [ ! ],
type the word DOCTYPE in all capital letters,
type the word html, and then close it.
Next, we need to open our HTML tag, and we'll go ahead and close that,
because everything is going to go inside of our HTML.
Next, we'll go ahead and open up a head tag, and we'll go ahead and close it,
and then right below that in just a moment, we'll go ahead and create our body tag.
First, however, there is a few things we need to put inside of our head tag.
What I'm going to type next is a little bit complicated.
I'll go ahead and type it first and then explain it.
There's a lot going on here.
First, we've created what's called a child element.
This tag is a child of its parent, which in this case is the head element.
It's a child, because it's nested inside between the opening head tag,
and the closing head tag.
This system of nesting will become more natural to you as we move along,
but it helps describe the relationship between elements.
Second, this element we just typed is called a meta-element,
often referred to as a meta-tag.
There are several types of meta-tags,
but in this case, we're using it to describe to the browser
what types of characters we'll be using.
This meta-tag is actually fairly technical,
so my recommendation for beginners is to simply copy this line
into the head section of your webpages exactly as you see it.
This is a special element called a self-closing tag,
because there's no ending tag that actually closes it.
It just closes itself.
Last, these parts inside of this particular meta-tag are called attributes.
An attribute simply describes an element in more detail.
We'll learn about some more useful and common attributes
as we move along.
Next, we're going to type up a title.
We'll create an opening and closing title tag,
and then inside we'll type &quot;Smells Like Bakin' Cupcake Company.&quot;
The title appears at the top of every webpage.
Let's go ahead and save that out.
We'll switch over to our web browser,
and if you keep an eye on the tab title when I refresh the page,
you'll see that it changes to &quot;Smells Like Bakin' Cupcake Company.&quot;
Now, let's stop for a minute and talk about web browsers.
The web browser I'm using is called Google Chrome.
You can use another web browser if you'd like,
such as Firefox, or Safari.
Sometimes web pages look slightly different depending on what web browser
they're being viewed in, but for these simpler web sites that we're working on,
any up-to-date browser should do just fine.
Remember, anytime you make a change to your text file,
you want to make sure that you refresh it in your web browser
so you can actually see the changes.
Let's go back to our text file and keep working.
We're all done with our head tag for now,
so let's go ahead and open up the body tag.
There's an open and closing body tag,
and that goes just below the head tag.
Notice that it is not nested inside like the title or meta-tags.
Now, inside of our body element,
we're going to create an image.
I'll type this out first and then explain it.
To create an image element, we just use img.
We don't actually type out the full word &quot;image.&quot;
Next, we have a few attributes--src, or &quot;source,&quot; and alt, or &quot;alternate.&quot;
The firs attribute, source, points to the location of an image file.
In this case, we have a folder called &quot;img&quot; and then inside of that folder
we have an image called logo with the file extension gif.
The second attribute is an alternate attribute.
For search engines or for individuals with vision impairments
that might not be able to see the image,
we can include text that describes what the image looks like,
or in this case, what our logo says.
Let's go ahead and save this file.
We'll see back to the browser and refresh the page,
and as you can see, we now have our image in the webpage.
Next, we're going to create our navigation as a list of items.
There are a few list-types you can create in HTML,
but the two basic ones are ordered lists
and unordered lists.
Ordered lists are numbered, and we don't need that in this case,
so we'll go ahead and create an unordered list.
Switching back to our text editor,
just below our image here we'll go ahead and open up an unordered list
or a ul tag, and then we'll go ahead and close our unordered list.
Inside of our unordered list, we need to create a few list items.
Now, I know in advance that we're going to have four navigational elements.
I'll go ahead and create four list items, using the li tag.
This is going to be exactly the same for all these,
so I'll just go ahead and copy and paste that three more times.
Inside of our li tag, we need to create some links
using what's called an anchor tag.
We'll learn more about links later on,
but for now we're just creating a website that has one page.
These links won't actually go anywhere.
We'll create a link for an about page.
We'll create another anchor tag or link.
And we'll say that links to cupcakes and prices.
We'll create another link.
And that will go to locations or places where you might find
a Smells Like Bakin' bakery.
Lastly, we'll create a contact page.
Like I said, we'll learn more about links later on,
but for now just type it exactly as you see it.
Next, we need to add a few attributes that we'll use
to select these elements with our CSS later on.
In this case, we're going to apply what are called class attributes.
So, next to my unordered list where it opens up
I'll type &quot;class,&quot; an equal sign, some quotes,
and then I'm going to type the word &quot;nav.&quot;
That way when I'm styling this with my CSS,
I'll be able to identify this particular unordered list as the navigation.
Then on my last list item I'm going to type the class &quot;last.&quot;
These classes are not predefined.
You can go ahead and name a class whatever you want and then refer to it later.
It's just an easy way of identifying things in your HTML with your CSS.
If that doesn't make any sense, don't worry.
It will when we move on to CSS.
With our navigation created as an unordered list,
let's go ahead and save.
We'll switch back to the browser and refresh,
and as you can see we now have a list of links.
We just learned a ton of HTML, and there's still more to go.
However, before we continue, let's stop for a minute
to review some of the things that we've learned.